

José Ignacio López Sáez

11/11/1986 - Age: 35

Married

Zapiola 3217 21A C1429ANG CABA

+54 9 11 3459 2012

ji.lopez.saez@gmail.com

https://tinyurl.com/ignacio-ls



JOSÉ IGNACIO LÓPEZ SÁEZ

MBA Candidate 2023, Data Science Specialist, Mg. in Project Assessment and Engineer, with proven capacity in areas of data analytics, BI, planning and reporting. Proficient in BI tools (PowerBI / Tableau), R / Python / SQL languages and Excel VBA development. Experienced team leader. Highly analytical and proactive profile.

Work Experience

Mar'22 - Present Shopee Argentina Fraud & Payments Data Analytics Lead – led a team of 3 associates ETL processes development and automatizacion (SQL / R / Python). Dashboard development. Monitoring & development of KPIs Fraud prevention model & strategies analysis Mar'21 - Present CoderHouse Professor of Analytics (SQL & PowerBI), BI & Data Analysis with Excel. Assistant Professor of Data Science Mar'15 - Present Instituto Tecnológico de Buenos Aires Assistant professor for Industrial Costs and Budget and Control, 4th year of Industrial Engineering. Oct'21 - Mar'22 Danone Data Analytics & EPM Leader - led a team of 4 analysts Feb'20 - Oct'21 **Buenos Aires City Government** In charge of data and analytics within the Sec. of Transport Monitoring & development of KPIs. Direct advisor to the Secretary of Transport. ETL scripts, dashboards dev. and reporting (Python + R + PowerBI) May'16 - Jan'20 Ministry of Transport In charge of data and analytics regarding the aero commercial industry: o 2018 - 2020: Director of Market Research and Data Analysis at Administración Nacional de Aviación Civil – **5 direct reports** o 2016 - 2018: Senior Statistical and Data Analyst at Empresa Argentina de Navegación Aérea SE (EANA SE). Monitoring of KPIs. Direct advisor to the Minister of Transport. Market research, short and long term demand forecasting. KPIs, dashboards and reports development: https://datos.anac.gob.ar/estadisticas/ Monitoring and analysis of the economics of the companies. Oil Combustibles Aug'14 - Apr'16

14 Apr 10 On Combastible

Commercial Planning Analyst. Main tasks performed:

- Short and long-term steel demand forecasting for the oil industry.
- Argentinian oil market analysis and studies. Impo/exports analysis.
- Support for commercial areas: local market offer & supply analysis.
- Pricing analysis and strategy definition. Annual budget analysis.

Feb'13 - Dec'13 **Ternium Siderar**

Commercial Planning Analyst. Main tasks performed:

- Short & long-term demand forecasting for the automotive industry.
- Direct and indirect steel and metal-mechanic products imports analysis. Competition studies. Global steel market studies.
- Assistance for Ternium's CEO and Siderar's General Director.



José Ignacio López Sáez

11/11/1986 – Age: 35

Married

Zapiola 3217 21A C1429ANG CABA

+54 9 11 3459 2012

ji.lopez.saez@gmail.com

https://tinyurl.com/ignacio-ls



JOSÉ IGNACIO LÓPEZ SÁEZ

MBA Candidate 2023, Data Science Specialist, Mg. in Project Assessment and Engineer, with proven capacity in areas of data analytics, BI, planning and reporting. Proficient in BI tools (PowerBI / Tableau), R / Python / SQL languages and Excel VBA development. Experienced team leader. Highly analytical and proactive profile.

Education	
2022 - 2023	MBA Candidate Universidad del CEMA
2020	PRE-QUANt - Python Programming Workshop for Finance Universidad del CEMA
2017 - 2018	Data Science Specialist Instituto Tecnológico de Buenos Aires (ITBA)
2014 - 2015	Magister in Project Assessment Instituto Tecnológico de Buenos Aires (ITBA) / Universidad del CEMA
2006 - 2011	Chemical Engineer Instituto Tecnológico de Buenos Aires (ITBA). GPA: 8.64 / 10.00 Double degree agreement with the <i>INSA</i> , Toulouse, France.
Languages	
English	 Excellent command of oral and written English: 2004: CAE Certificate of Advanced English 2014: IELTS International English Language Testing System. Band 8.
French	Excellent command of oral and written French: 2011: DALF C1 Diplome Approfondi de la Langue Française
Skills	
BI	Advanced command of the following BI suites and tools: Power BI Tableau Qlik Ms Power Query & Power Pivot and Ms Excel.
Coding	Vast experience working and coding (for data analysis & research) with:

Interests

DB

Running	Road and trail runner (amateur, but passionate):
	 42k Mar del Plata 2013/14/15/18/19
	 42k Buenos Aires 2014/15/16/17/18/19/21
	 42k Córdoba 2015
	 42k Santiago de Chile 2016
	 42k Rosario 2017
	 42k Montevideo 2018
	 50k TNFEC San Martín de los Andes 2015
	 100k Cruce de los Andes 2016
	 60k Raid de los Andes 2017
	 75k UTACCH Villa Yacanto 2016

R & Python

Visual Basic – (Ms Excel macros)

Presto SQL / PostgreSQL / Ms SQL Server

110k UTACCH Villa Yacanto 2018/19